Guide to the Carolyn Ratcliffe Collection on La Plaza Cultural 1980s-2006 MS 3051
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Carolyn Ratcliffe collection on La Plaza Cultural
1980s-2006
MS 3051
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
3.0 Linear feet in three record cartons
La Plaza Cultural de Armando Perez is located on the Lower East Side of the Manhattan borough of New York City. Founded in 1976 on the site of an abandoned city lot, the space has become an outdoor community garden, space for play and social gathering, and a performance venue. The collection includes photographs, ephemera and working papers from the files of Carolyn Ratcliffe, an officer in the 1990s to early 2000s of the non-profit organization formed to rebuild the La Plaza Cultural site, acquire grants, and develop programming there. Photographs are the core of the collection and include images of performances; community celebrations of Halloween, springtime, and other occasions; sculpture and other artwork; people gardening, building, and doing other work in the space, as well as enjoying leisure activities; flowers and other plants in the garden; and other related subject matter.
Ratcliffe, Carolyn
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
Gift of Carolyn Ratcliffe, June 2016.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. The collection includes some digital formats (zip drives, 3.55" floppy disks, and CDs) and those are currently restricted from access in order to ensure that the files are not accidentally corrupted.
Biographical/Historical Note
La Plaza Cultural de Armando Perez (La Plaza Cultural) is located at the corner of East 9th Street and Avenue C on the Lower East Side of the Manhattan borough of New York City. Occupying a large corner lot, La Plaza Cultural is an outdoor community garden, space for play and social gathering, and a performance venue. It began in 1976 when an artist in the area, Gordon La Matta Clark, led a neighborhood effort to clean up an abandoned lot that had been the site of since-demolished buildings. Into the 1980s, the site developed into a park, with garden and theatre space. By the late 1980s, though, real estate interests sought to rebuild on the site. This led to a series of court battles, ending eventually in 2003 with a settlement that ensured La Plaza Cultural's survival.
Through the 1990s and into the early 2000s, as the court fights went on, the programs at La Plaza Cultural did also. A non-profit, the 600 B/C East Ninth Street Block Association, was formed and incorporated to rebuild the park and manage programs, such as the performance of "Demeter's Daughter" in 1997 and the annual Halloween celebration. Among the active members of this non-profit was Carolyn Ratcliffe, a resident of the La Plaza Cultural neighborhood. Ratcliffe was elected Chairperson of the association in 1990 and held various official positions with the organization over the next thirteen years until the 2003 legal victory. Over that period, she acquired various grants in support of La Plaza Cultural's programming, organized many of the programs, wrote publicity materials in support of the organization and site, and was an overall active participant in building La Plaza Cultural's role in the community while defending it from development.
Arrangement Note
The collection is arranged with photographs and other images first, followed by working files, and then digital formats, which are currently restricted.
Most of the photographs are snapshots. Those found together in albums or packets were retained together. Many though were loose. Photographs that were explicitly dated are presented first, followed by undated photographs. Loose photographs were compiled together by the processing archivist based on IDs or other markings on their reverse in an attempt to bring together like subject matter. These are compiled together in envelopes that note the linking ID. Photographs with no linking ID were sorted by rough subject.
Photographic slides were found in a series of small boxes and a carousel. The slides were moved to a sleeve, keeping together those slides found in particular boxes. The boxes were identified arbitrarily by letter, A to P, and that designation was noted on the slide sleeves.
The working files were found in unlabeled plastic folders; during processing the content was moved to archival folders. In the container list, these are all summarized in one entry. In the box itself, each folder retains the content of the original file. The original files were identified arbitrarily by the archivist by letter, A to E, and that designation was noted on the folder.
Scope and Contents note
The collection includes photographs, ephemera and working papers from the files of Carolyn Ratcliffe relating to the history of La Plaza Cultural de Armando Perez. The bulk of the collection dates from the mid 1990s to about 2003, with much of this material being photographs. The photographs include images of performances; community celebrations of Halloween, springtime, and other occasions; sculpture and other artwork; people gardening, building, and doing other work in the space, as well as enjoying leisure activities; flowers and other plants in the garden; and other related subject matter. Most of the photographs are color print snapshots; other formats include slides and negatives. Some of the photographs and other images were gathered into albums.
The collection also includes at least some of Ratcliffe's working files. These primarily include documents related to grant funding proposals, reports to project funders, financial summaries, contact lists, and other administrative matters. Among the programs and grants represented in these files are the La Plaza Cultural Environmental Living Lab Program, Community Assets grants from the New York Foundation for the Arts, and Neighborhood Open Space Management grants from The Trust for Public Land. The files include letters received from schoolchildren at PS 188 who participated in a gardening curriculum in 2003.
The collection also includes small posters and other publicity materials related to events at La Plaza. Also, the collection holds several digital formats, including zip drives, floppy disks, and CDs, that are labeled as holding photographs, brochures, hard drive back-ups, contact lists, and other matter; access to these is currently restricted in order to avoid the risk of corrupting or otherwise damaging the files.
La Plaza Cultural (New York, N.Y.).; Community gardens -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs; Theater, Open-air -- New York (State) -- New York
- "Viva La Plaza: Growing a Garden, Building a Community", circa 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents Note
  Overview booklet with a history of La Plaza, press clippings, letters of reference, renovation drawings, images, and other material.
- Photograph and Ephemera Albums (5 folders), 1980s?-circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
- Save the Garden Benefit Photographs, 1990s? (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Rites of Spring Images, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Photographs: Snapshots - Dated (12 folders), 1993-2002 (Box 1, Folder 9-20)
- Photographs: Snapshots - Undated (6 of 7 folders), circa 1990s-2001 (Box 1, Folder 21-26)
- Photographs: Snapshots - Undated (1 of 7 folders), circa 1990s-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photographs: Slides (4 folders), circa 1990s-2001 (Box 2, Folder 2-5)
- Oversize Posters and Other Graphic Material, circa 1990s-2001 (Box Oversize-Small)
- Photographs: Negatives (3 folders), circa 1990s-2001 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
- Photographs: Film Rolls (RESTRICTED), circa 1990s-2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Includes small rolls of film from the collection, which cannot be viewed.
- General Working Files (10 folders), 1992-2003 (Box 2, Folder 10-19)
- Wall Image Proposal, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Armando Perez Street Naming Ceremony, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Ephemera, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Digital Formats (RESTRICTED), circa 1990s-2002 (Box 3)
  Includes zip drives, CDs, and 3.5" floppy disks.These are currently restricted from access in order to ensure that the digital files are not accidentally corrupted.